So my moment of truth
إذا لحظة الحقيقة
did not come all at once.
لم تأتي مرة واحدة
In 2010, I had the chance to be considered
في 2010, سنحت لي الفرصة
for promotion from my job
لأترقى في عملي
as director of policy planning
كمراقبة للتخطيط السياسي
at the U.S. State Department.
في وزارة الخارجية الأمريكية
This was my moment to lean in,
كانت هذه اللحظة التي اعتمدت عليها
to push myself forward
للمضي قدمــًا
for what are really only a handful
لأجل ما يعتبر حفنة
of the very top foreign policy jobs,
من الوظائف المتوفرة في سياسات التخطيط الخارجية,
and I had just finished a big, 18-month project
و انتهيت فقط من مشروع كبير اتخذ 18 شهرًا
for Secretary Clinton, successfully,
للوزيرة هيلاري كلنتون, بنجاح
and I knew I could handle a bigger job.
و عرفت انه بإمكاني أن اقوم بوظيفة اكبر
The woman I thought I was
المرأة التي ظننت أنني كنت
would have said yes.
كانت ستقبل
But I had been commuting for two years
لكني قضيت وقتـــًا في المواصلات لمدة عامين
between Washington and Princeton, New Jersey,
بين واشنطون بيرنستون و نيوجيرسي
where my husband and my two teenage sons lived,
حيث اقام زوجي وابناي التوأم المراهقين
and it was not going well.
لم يسر الأمر على مايرام
I tried on the idea of eking out another two years
حاولت أن اقتصد في عامين اخرين
in Washington, or maybe uprooting my sons
في واشنطون او أنزع ابنائي
from their school and my husband from his work
من مدارسهم وزوجي من عمله
and asking them to join me.
و أن اطلب منهم الإنضمام إلي
But deep down, I knew
لكن داخلي عرفت
that the right decision was to go home,
ان القرار الصحيح ان ابقى في البيت
even if I didn't fully recognize the woman
بالرغم من انني لم اتعرف على المرأة
who was making that choice.
التي صنعت القرار
That was a decision based on love
إلا أنه كان قرارًا مبنيًا على الحب
and responsibility.
والمسؤلية
I couldn't keep watching my oldest son
لم استطيع مراقبة ابني الكبير
make bad choices
يتخذ قرارات سيئة
without being able to be there for him
ولا استطيع ان اكون معه
when and if he needed me.
عندما يحتاجني
But the real change came more gradually.
لكن التغير الحقيقي اتى تدريجيًا
Over the next year,
خلال السنة القادمة
while my family was righting itself,
عندما كانت عائلتي تقوم نفسها
I started to realize
بدأت ادرك
that even if I could go back into government,
حتى إن استطعت العودة إلى الحكومة
I didn't want to.
لا أريد
I didn't want to miss the last five years
ان اضيع الخمسة اعوام الأخيرة
that my sons were at home.
التي سيقضيها ابنائي في المنزل
I finally allowed myself to accept
اخيرًا سمحت لنفسي بقبول
what was really most important to me,
ماهو مهم حقًا بالنسبة لي
not what I was conditioned to want
وليست رغباتي المشروطة
or maybe what I conditioned myself to want,
او ربما الرغبات التي شرطتها لنفسي
and that decision led to a reassessment
والقرار أدى لإعادة تقيم
of the feminist narrative that I grew up with
السرد النسوي الذي نشأت فيه
and have always championed.
والذي دافعت عنه دائمًا
I am still completely committed
مازلت ملتزمة تمامًا
to the cause of male-female equality,
لهدف المساواة بين الرجل والمراة
but let's think about what that equality really means,
لكن دعونا نفكر ماذا تعني هذه المساواة حقــًا
and how best to achieve it.
وما أفضل طريقة لإنجازها
I always accepted the idea
دائمــًا قبلت بفكرة
that the most respected and powerful people
ان معظم الأشخاص المؤثرين والمحترمين
in our society are men at the top of their careers,
في مجتمعنا رجال يتصدرون المراتب الأولى في وظائفهم
so that the measure of male-female equality
إذن مقياس المساواة بين الرجل والمرأة
ought to be how many women are in those positions:
يجب ان تكون ماعدد النساء الذين يحتلون هذه الوظائف
prime ministers, presidents, CEOs,
رؤساء وزراء, رؤســاء, رؤساء تنفيذين
directors, managers, Nobel laureates, leaders.
مراقبين, مدراء, حائزين على جائزة نوبل, قيادين
I still think we should do everything we possibly can
مازلت اظن اننا يجب ان نفعل كل ما بإمكاننا
to achieve that goal.
حتى نحقق هذا الهدف
But that's only half of real equality,
لكن هذا فقط نصف المساواة الحقيقية
and I now think we're never going to get there
والان افكر لن نستطيع ابدًا ان نكون هنالك
unless we recognize the other half.
مالم نعترف بالنصف الأخر
I suggest that real equality,
اقترح ان المساواة الحقيقية
full equality,
المساواة الكاملة
does not just mean valuing women
لاتعني فقط تقيم النساء
on male terms.
بمصطلحات ذكورية
It means creating a much wider range
هي تعني إنشاء نطاق واسع
of equally respected choices
من خيارات المساواة المحترمة
for women and for men.
للنساء والرجال
And to get there, we have to change our workplaces,
وحتى نصل لهذا علينا ان نغير اماكن العمل
our policies and our culture.
سياساتنا وثقافاتنا
In the workplace,
في اماكن العمل
real equality means valuing family
المساواة الحقيقية تعني تقدير العائلة
just as much as work,
تمامــًا كما العمل
and understanding that the two reinforce each other.
و فهم ان كلاهما يعززان بعضهما
As a leader and as a manager,
كقائدة ومديرة
I have always acted on the mantra,
دائمــًا تصرفت تبعًا للتعويذة
if family comes first,
إذا تقدمت العائلة اولاً
work does not come second --
لايجب على العمل ان يأتي ثانيًا
life comes together.
الحياة تأتي كاملة
If you work for me, and you have a family issue,
إذا كنت تعمل لدي ولديك مسائل عائلية
I expect you to attend to it,
اتوقع منك ان تهتم بها
and I am confident,
انا واثقة
and my confidence has always been borne out,
وثقتي دائمـــًا يعززها
that the work will get done, and done better.
ان العمل سينجز, و سينجز افضل
Workers who have a reason to get home
الموظفون الذين لديهم سبب كي يعودوا إلى المنزل
to care for their children or their family members
كي يهتموا بأطفالهم و أفراد اسرتهم
are more focused, more efficient,
اكثر تركيزًا وفعالية
more results-focused.
نتائجهم اكثر تركيز
And breadwinners who are also caregivers
معيلين لأسرهم و أيضًا مهتمين بهم
have a much wider range
لديهم أيضًا نطاق واسع
of experiences and contacts.
من الخبرة والإتصالات
Think about a lawyer who spends part of his time
فكر في المحامي الذي يقضي جزءًا من وقته
at school events for his kids
في احداث اطفاله المدرسية
talking to other parents.
متحدثــًا إلى الأباء الأخرين
He's much more likely to bring in
إنه من المحتمل جدًا ان
new clients for his firm
يحضر عملاء جدد
than a lawyer who never leaves his office.
مقارنة بمحامي لايغادر مكتبه أبدًا
And caregiving itself
والإهتمام بالعائلة
develops patience --
ينمي الصبر
a lot of patience --
الكثير من الصبر
and empathy, creativity, resilience, adaptability.
التعاطف و الإبداع و المرونة والتكيف
Those are all attributes that are ever more important
هذه هي الصفات الأكثر اهمية
in a high-speed, horizontal,
في الإقتصاد العالمي المتشعب
networked global economy.
افقيــًا والسريع جدًا
The best companies actually know this.
افضل الشركات حقيقة تعرف ذلك
The companies that win awards
الشركات التي تكسب الجوائز
for workplace flexibility in the United States
لأماكن العمل الأكثر مرونة في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
include some of our most successful corporations,
تتضمن اكثر شركاتنا نجاحًا
and a 2008 national study
ايضًا 2008 دراسة وطنية
on the changing workforce
عن التغير في مكان العمل
showed that employees
اظهرت ان الموظفين
in flexible and effective workplaces
في اماكن العمل الأكثر مرونة وفعالية
are more engaged with their work,
اكثر إلتزامــًا بعملهم
they're more satisfied and more loyal,
هم اكثر رضاءًا و ولاء
they have lower levels of stress
لديهم مستويات اقل من القلق
and higher levels of mental health.
ومستويات اعلى من الصحة العقلية
And a 2012 study of employers
أيضًا 2012 دراسة للموظفين
showed that deep, flexible practices
اظهرت ان الممارسات المتعمقة المرنة
actually lowered operating costs
قللت فعلاً من تكاليف التشغيل
and increased adaptability
و زادت من التكيف
in a global service economy.
مع خدمات الإقتصاد العالمي
So you may think
إذن لربما ظننت
that the privileging of work over family
تفضيل العمل على العائلة
is only an American problem.
مشكلة امريكية فقط
Sadly, though, the obsession with work
مع ذلك محزن ان هاجس العمل
is no longer a uniquely American disease.
لم يعد مرضًا امريكيًا
Twenty years ago,
عشرون عامًا فيما مضى
when my family first started going to Italy,
عندما بدأت عائلتي بالذهاب لإيطاليا
we used to luxuriate in the culture of siesta.
كنا نترفه في ثقافة القيلولة
Siesta is not just about avoiding the heat of the day.
القيلولة ليست فقط لتجنب هجير النهار
It's actually just as much
إنها في الواقع بنفس القدر
about embracing the warmth of a family lunch.
عن إغتنام حميمية الغداء العائلي
Now, when we go, fewer and fewer businesses
الان, عندما نذهب القليل والقليل من المشاريع
close for siesta,
تغلق للقيلولة
reflecting the advance of global corporations
عاكستــًا التطور للشركات العالمية
and 24-hour competition.
و طبيعة المنافسة على مدار ال 24 ساعة
So making a place for those we love
إذن صنع مكان لألئك الذين نحبهم
is actually a global imperative.
في الحقيقة هو عائق عالمي
In policy terms,
بمفهوم سياسي
real equality means recognizing
المساواة الحقيقية تعني الإعتراف
that the work that women have traditionally done
بأن العمل الذي تقوم به النساء تقليديًا
is just as important
مهم فقط كما
as the work that men have traditionally done,
كما العمل الذي يقوم به الرجال تقليديًا
no matter who does it.
لا يهم من يقوم به
Think about it: Breadwinning and caregiving
اعتبر ان الإعالة والإهتمام
are equally necessary for human survival.
مهمان سويَا للبقاء الإنساني
At least if we get beyond a barter economy,
على الأقل إذا تخطينا إقتصاد المقايضة
somebody has to earn an income
على احد الما ان يكسب عائدًا
and someone else has to convert that income
وعلى شخص اخر ان يحول هذا الدخل
to care and sustenance for loved ones.
إلى رعاية و مساندة للأحباب
Now most of you, when you hear me
الان معظمكم عندما تسمعونني
talk about breadwinning and caregiving,
اتحدث عن الإعالة والإهتمام
instinctively translate those categories
غريزيــًا تترجمون هذه الصفات
into men's work and women's work.
إلى عمل رجالي وعمل نسائي
And we don't typically challenge
و نحن عادة لا نختبر
why men's work is advantaged.
تفضيل عمل الرجال
But consider a same-sex couple
لكن اعتبروا زوجيين مثليين
like my friends Sarah and Emily.
كما صديقتاي ايميلي وسارة
They're psychiatrists.
هما طبيبتان نفسيتان
They got married five years ago,
تزوجتا منذ ثمانية اعوام
and now they have two-year-old twins.
والأن لديهما توأمان
They love being mothers,
هما تحبان ان تصبحان والدتان
but they also love their work,
لكنهما ايضًا تحبان عملهما
and they're really good at what they do.
وهما ايضًا ماهرتان في عملهما
So how are they going to divide up
إذن كيف سيقتسمان
breadwinning and caregiving responsibilities?
مسؤليات الإعالة والرعاية؟
Should one of them stop working
هل لابد لإحدهما ان تتوقف عن العمل
or reduce hours to be home?
او ان تقلل ساعاتها لتمكث في المنزل؟
Or should they both change their practices
ام لابد لكلتاهما ان تغيرا مجالهما
so they can have much more flexible schedules?
حتى يكون لديهما ساعات عمل اكثر مرونة؟
And what criteria should they use
وأية معيار عليهما ان تستخدما
to make that decision?
لإتخاذ القرار؟
Is it who makes the most money
هل هو الشخص الذي يكسب اكثر
or who is most committed to her career?
ام الشخص الذي اكثر إلتزامــًا بالعمل
Or who has the most flexible boss?
ام الشخص الذي لديه مدير اكثر مرونة؟
The same-sex perspective helps us see
منظور المثليين يساعدنا لنرى
that juggling work and family
ان الموازنة بين العمل والعائلة
are not women's problems,
ليست مشكلة المرأة
they're family problems.
هي مشكلة العائلة
And Sarah and Emily are the lucky ones,
ايـضًا سارة وايملي محظوظتان
because they have a choice
لان لديهما خيار
about how much they want to work.
حول مقدار العمل الذي تريدان
Millions of men and women
ملايين النساء والرجال
have to be both breadwinners and caregivers
عليهم ان يكونوا عائلين ورعائين معًا
just to earn the income they need,
حتى يكسبوا الدخل الذي يحتاجون
and many of those workers are scrambling.
والعديد من هؤلاء الموظفين مندفعين
They're patching together care arrangements
هم يرقعون معًا تدابير للرعاية
that are inadequate
غير ملائمة
and often actually unsafe.
وغالبًا غير امنة
If breadwinning and caregiving are really equal,
إذا كانت الإعالة والرعاية متساوية
then why shouldn't a government
إذن لماذا لاينبغى على الحكومة
invest as much in an infrastructure of care
ان تستثمر قدرًا في بنية تحتية للرعاية
as the foundation of a healthy society
كدعامة لمجتمع صحي
as it invests in physical infrastructure
كما تستثمر في البنيات التحتية
as the backbone of a successful economy?
كعمود فقري لإقتصاد ناجح
The governments that get it --
الحكومات التي تتخذها
no surprises here --
ليس من المستغرب هنا
the governments that get it,
ان الحكومات التي تتخدها
Norway, Sweden, Denmark, the Netherlands,
النرويج السويد الدنمارك و هولندا
provide universal child care,
توفر خدمات رعاية شاملة للطفل
support for caregivers at home,
دعم للرعائين في المنزل
school and early childhood education,
و المدرسة ومراحل تعليم الطفولة المبكرة
protections for pregnant women,
حماية للحوامل
and care for the elderly and the disabled.
و رعاية للكهول وذوي الإحتياجات الخاصة
Those governments invest in that infrastructure
هذه الحكومات تستثمر في البنيات التحتية
the same way they invest in roads and bridges
بنفس الطريقة التي تستثمر في الطرق والجسور
and tunnels and trains.
والقطارات والأنفاق
Those societies also show you
هذه المجتمعات ايضًا تريكم
that breadwinning and caregiving
أن الإعالة والرعاية
reinforce each other.
تعززان بعضهما
They routinely rank among the top 15 countries
بشكل روتيني هم يتصدرون ترتيب عالي بين 15 دولة
of the most globally competitive economies,
من اكثر الدول اقتصاداتها قادرة على المنافسة عالميًا
but at the same time,
لكن في نفس الوقت
they rank very high on the OECD Better Life Index.
هم ايضًا يتصدرون عاليًا في مؤشر الحياة في منظمة التعاون والتنمية
In fact, they rank higher than other governments,
في الحقيقة هم يتصدرون مراتب اعلى مقارنة بحكومات اخرى
like my own, the U.S., or Switzerland,
كحكومتي, الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية او سويسرا
that have higher average levels of income
التي لديها معدلات دخل أعلى
but lower rankings on work-life balance.
لكن مرتبة اقل في الموازنة مابين العمل والحياة
So changing our workplaces
إذن تغيير أماكن عملنا
and building infrastructures of care
وبناء بنية تحتية للرعاية
would make a big difference,
بإمكانه احداث تغير كبير
but we're not going to get equally valued choices
لكننا لن نحصل على قيمة متساوية من الخيارت
unless we change our culture,
إلا إذا غيرنا ثقافتنا
and the kind of cultural change required
ونوع التغير الثقافي المطلوب
means re-socializing men.
يعني إعادة تنشئة الرجال إجتماعيًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Increasingly in developed countries,
بصورة متصاعدة في الدول المتقدمة
women are socialized to believe that our place
النساء ينشئون إجتماعيًا لتصديق ان مكانهن
is no longer only in the home,
لم يعد في البيت فقط,
but men are actually still where they always were.
لكن الرجال مازالوا في نفس المكان الذي كانوا فيه دائمًا
Men are still socialized to believe
الرجال مازالوا ينشئون إجتماعيًا لتصديق
that they have to be breadwinners,
أن عليهم العمل لكسب الرغيف
that to derive their self-worth
ان يستمدوا تقديرهم لذواتهم
from how high they can climb over other men
من علو الإرتقاء الذي يحرزونه فوق الرجال الأخرين
on a career ladder.
على السلم الوظيفي
The feminist revolution still has a long way to go.
النهضة النسوية لديها طريق طويل لتمضي
It's certainly not complete.
بكل تأكيد هو غير مكتمل
But 60 years after
لكن 60 عاماً
"The Feminine Mystique" was published,
بعد نشر" لغز النسوية"
many women actually have
العديد من النساء لديهن حقيقة
more choices than men do.
خيارت اكثر من الرجال
We can decide to be a breadwinner,
بإمكاننا ان نقرر ان نصبح عائلين
a caregiver, or any combination of the two.
رعائيين, او اي خليط من الإثنين
When a man, on the other hand,
من الناحية الأخرى عندما الرجل
decides to be a caregiver,
يقرر ان يصبح رعائيًا
he puts his manhood on the line.
هو يضع رجولته على الخط
His friends may praise his decision,
اصدقائه لربما اشادوا بقراره
but underneath, they're scratching their heads.
لكنهم سرًا يحكون رؤسهم
Isn't the measure of a man
أليس مقياس الرجل
his willingness to compete with other men
مقدرته على منافسة رجل اخر
for power and prestige?
لأجل النفوذ والهيبة
And as many women hold that view as men do.
أيضًا العديد من النساء يحملن نفس وجهة النظر كما الرجال
We know that lots of women
نحن نعرف ان الكثير من النساء
still judge the attractiveness of a man
مازلن يحكمن على جاذبية الرجل
based in large part on how successful he is
إستنادًا على جزء كبير من مقدار نجاحه
in his career.
في عمله
A woman can drop out of the work force
المرأة بإمكانها ان تترك القوة العاملة
and still be an attractive partner.
وتحافظ على جاذبيتها كشريك.
For a man, that's a risky proposition.
بالنسبة للرجل هذا مقترح خطير
So as parents and partners,
كوالد و كشريك
we should be socializing our sons
علينا ان ننشأ إجتماعيًا ابنائنا
and our husbands
و أزواجنا
to be whatever they want to be,
على ان يكونوا مايرغبون
either caregivers or breadwinners.
إما رعائين او معيلين
We should be socializing them to make caregiving
علينا ان ننشئهم إجتماعيًا لنجعل الرعاية
cool for guys.
امر جيد للرجال.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I can almost hear lots of you thinking, "No way."
بإستطاعتي ان اسمع العديد منكم يفكرون, " مستحيل"
But in fact, the change is actually already happening.
لكن في الحقيقة, التغير قد حدث
At least in the United States,
على الأقل في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
lots of men take pride in cooking,
الكثير من الرجال يفتخرون بالطبخ
and frankly obsess over stoves.
و بصدق يحبون المواقد
They are in the birthing rooms.
هم في غرفات الولادة.
They take paternity leave when they can.
يأخذون إجازات ابوة عندما يستطيعون
They can walk a baby or soothe a toddler
بإمكانهم تمشية الرضيع او تسكين الطفل
just as well as their wives can,
بنفس الطريقة التي بإمكان زوجاتهم
and they are increasingly
وهم بتزايد
doing much more of the housework.
يقومون بالكثير من اعمال المنزل
Indeed, there are male college students now
بالتأكيد هنالك طلاب جامعة ذكور الان
who are starting to say,
ابتدأوا يقولون
"I want to be a stay-at-home dad."
" اريد ان اكون اب مقيم في المنزل"
That was completely unthinkable
كان هذا غير وارد تمامًا
50 or even 30 years ago.
في 50 او حتى 30 عاماً فيما مضى
And in Norway, where men have
و في النرويج, حيث الرجال لديهم
an automatic three month's paternity leave,
إجازة ابوة تلقائية لمدة ثلاثة اشهر
but they lose it if they decide not to take it,
لكنهم يخسرونها إذا لم ياخذوها
a high government official told me
مسؤول رفيع اخبرني
that companies are starting to look
ان الشركات بدأت بالنظر
at prospective male employees
إلى الموظفين المرتقبين الذكور
and raise an eyebrow if they didn't in fact
وتقطيب جبينهم إذا
take their leave when they had kids.
لم يأخذوا إجازة المغادرة عندما رزقوا بابناء
That means that it's starting to seem
هذا يعني انه بدأ يظهر
like a character defect
كنقص في الشخصية
not to want to be a fully engaged father.
أن لا تريد ان تكون والدًا ملتزمـًا بالكلية
So I was raised
إذن تربيت
to believe that championing women's rights
لأصدق ان المدافعين عن حقوق المرأة
meant doing everything we could
قصدوا ان نقوم بكل شيء نستطيعه
to get women to the top.
حتى نأخذ النساء للقمة
And I still hope that I live long enough
و مازلت امل ان اعيش مطولاَ
to see men and women equally represented
حتى ارى الرجال والنساء يعرضون بتساوي
at all levels of the work force.
في جميع قوى العمل
But I've come to believe that we have to value family
لكنني وصلت للإعتقاد انه يجب علينا ان نقدر العائلة
every bit as much as we value work,
بكل شيء بقدر مانقدر العمل
and that we should entertain the idea
وأنه علينا ان نرحب بفكرة
that doing right by those we love
ان اعطاء الذين نحبهم حقهم
will make all of us better at everything we do.
سيجعلنا افضل في كل شيء نعمله
Thirty years ago, Carol Gilligan,
ثلاثون عامًا ماضية كارول جيليغان
a wonderful psychologist, studied adolescent girls
طبيبة نفسية رائعة درست المراهقة لدى الفتيات
and identified an ethic of care,
و حددت اخلاقيات الرعاية
an element of human nature every bit as important
عنصرًا في الطبيعة الإنسانية مهم في كل شيء
as the ethic of justice.
كما اخلاقيات العدالة
It turns out that "you don't care"
يتبدا لنا " انت لا تهتم"
is just as much a part of who we are
هي بنفس القدر جزء منا
as "that's not fair."
كما " انت لست عادل"
Bill Gates agrees.
يتفق مع ذلك بيل غيتس
He argues that the two great forces of human nature
هو يناقش ان اكبر قوتين للطبيعة الإنسانية
are self-interest and caring for others.
هما المصلحة الذاتية والإهتمام بالأخرين
Let's bring them both together.
دعونا نجمع بينهما
Let's make the feminist revolution
ونجعل النهضة النسوية
a humanist revolution.
نهضة إنسانية
As whole human beings,
كلنا كبشر
we will be better caregivers and breadwinners.
سنكون افضل رعائين وعائلين
You may think that can't happen,
لربما ظننت ان هذا لن يحدث
but I grew up in a society
لكني نشأت في مجتمع
where my mother put out small vases
حيث كانت تضع طفايات
of cigarettes for dinner parties,
سجائر على موائد العشاء الإحتفالية
where blacks and whites used separate bathrooms,
حيث استخدم السود والبيض حمامات منفصلة
and where everybody claimed to be heterosexual.
وكل شخص ادعى انه غير مثلي جنسيًا
Today, not so much.
اليوم , لا يتواجد بكثرة.
The revolution for human equality
النهضة لأجل المساواة الإنسانية
can happen.
بإمكانها ان تحدث
It is happening.
هي تحدث
It will happen.
وسوف تحدث
How far and how fast is up to us.
إلى اي مدى وسرعة الأمر يرجع لنا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)